好的，距离谷歌发布 Gemini 3 系列模型之一 Gemini Flash 已经过去 64 天多了，
Okay, so it's been over 64 days since Google released one of the Gemini 3 models and that was
而距离他们发布 Gemini 3 Pro 大约也有 30 天了。也就是说，Gemini 3 发布至今
the Gemini Flash. And about 30 days before that they released Gemini 3 Pro. So we're coming up
已经快 100 天了。在当今的人工智能生态系统中，这几乎相当于 100 年那么久。
on nearly 100 days of Gemini 3 being out. And you've got to think in the current AI
所以今天，谷歌正式推出了 Gemini 3.1 Pro。在本视频中，我将带大家了解这个模型的一些更新内容。
sort of ecosystem that is the equivalent to like 100 years. So today Google is introducing
简单聊聊它如何融入当前的发布节奏，并快速看看这个模型的实际能力——
Gemini 3.1 Pro. And in this video I'm going to go through some of the updates with this model.
目前它已经开始逐步部署到大多数使用 Gemini 模型的谷歌应用中。
Talk a little bit about how this fits in with the release schedule. And we'll have a quick look at
我们来看看官方博客文章，会发现一些有趣的信息。
what this model can actually do as it's now being rolled out to most of the Google apps that use
首先，这个版本号是 3.1，本身就很有意思，对吧？
Gemini model. So if we come in and look at the blog post about this we can see some sort of
因为 Gemini 之前从未有过 0.1 这样的版本，只有 0 或 0.5 这样的发布。
interesting things. So the first off just the fact this is a 3.1 as it is kind of interesting,
这是首次出现 0.1 版本。我觉得这很耐人寻味，
right? Gemini has never had anything except sort of like a zero release or a 0.5 release.
毕竟距离该模型的初版发布已经快 100 天了。
This is the first time we've seen a 0.1 release. I do think that's kind of interesting in the fact
显然，在这段时间里，Gemini 深度思考模型取得了巨大进展，
that it is nearly 100 days since the first version of this model has come out. Clearly in that time
而他们显然正在将这些理念和技术融入主力的 Pro 模型中。
they've made a lot of impact with the Gemini deep think models. And they are clearly taking some
好，现在我们来看看基准测试数据。我认为关键不在于把它和其他模型对比，
of those ideas and some of that technology and putting it into the main pro model here.
虽然他们确实拿它和 Sonnet 4.6、Opus 4.6 以及 GPT 系列做了比较。
Okay, so if we come in and look at the benchmarks here I think the real takeaway here is not
真正重要的是和 Gemini 3 Pro 的对比，这样才看得出变化。
just comparing this to other models. So they certainly compare this to Sonnet 4.6 and Opus 4.6
比如看“人类最终考试”（Humanity's Last Exam）这项测试，相比 Gemini 3 Pro 有巨大提升。
as well as the GPT models. But it's really comparing to Gemini 3 Pro that we can sort of see
没错，它超过了 Sonnet 4.6，也超过了 Opus 4.6，
stuff. So if we look at, for example, the humanity's last exam, this is a huge bump over Gemini 3 Pro.
但更值得关注的是它相对于 Gemini 3 Pro 的飞跃式进步。
Yes, it's more than Sonnet 4.6. Yes, it's more than Opus 4.6. But look at the bump that we're
别忘了，这还只是一个 .1 版本！
seeing compared to Gemini 3 Pro. And don't forget this is just a .1 release, right? And I'd say the
我认为主要原因在于——稍后我会展示一些例子——
main reason for that is like I'll show you in a second when we actually do some look at some examples
它内置的“高思维模式”本质上就像是一个轻量版的深度思考模型。
that this thinking high mode in here really is like a deep think mini kind of thing that they've
我们在 Arc AGI 测试中也能看到类似趋势：77% 对比 Gemini 3 Pro 的 31%。
got going on here. We can see this also when we look at like the Arc AGI. Arc AGI, 77% compared to 31%
当然，Anthropic 的模型当时表现更好，
with Gemini 3 Pro. Obviously, you know, the anthropic models were doing a lot better than that.
但谷歌可能根本没想过要用 Gemini 3 Pro 去优化这类任务。
Google probably hadn't really sort of even thought about optimizing for this maybe with Gemini 3 Pro.
不过现在我们可以看到这里有了巨大飞跃。
But we can see that this has got a huge bump here. And while Google's not saying this sort of,
虽然谷歌在博客里没明说，但这明显表明他们已经开始构建非常强大的
you know, in their blog post, this definitely looks like that they're starting to get really good
强化学习（RL）训练环境，用于这类任务，从而带来更好的基准测试成绩。
RL environments for training these kinds of tasks, which then translate to better benchmarks.
我们在其他需要 RL 环境的任务中也能看到这一点，
We see this also when we look at, you know, some of the other things which would have RL environments
比如编码基准测试，或者像 MCP Atlas 这样的场景——你可以想象其中涉及代理式搜索等等。
like coding bench, like things like this MCP Atlas where you could imagine that you're doing that
显然，不仅是基准测试在展示进步。
like the agentic search, et cetera. So clearly we're seeing, you know, just not just benchmarks
我们也能看到，比如在生成设计内容方面，3.1 Pro 已经明显优于 3 Pro。
show this off. We can see here that, okay, you know, getting it to generate things for designs,
这同样可以想象是通过高质量的 RL 环境实现的。
3.1 Pro is already looking a lot better than 3 Pro. Again, this is something that you could
同样的情况也出现在图形设计、编码等相关领域——
imagine having been done with a really good RL environment. Same for sort of, you know,
我们可以看到模型在这些方面确实进步了。
graphic designs on coding and stuff like that, we can see that, okay, the model's gotten better
不过除此之外，谷歌其实没透露太多信息，对吧？
with those sorts of things. Now, apart from this Google's not actually saying a lot here, right?
所以这就很有意思了：正如我前面所说，这是个 .1 版本。
So it is kind of interesting that like I said, this is a .1 release. Perhaps in the past,
过去他们可能会直接说：“这是又一个新的 Gemini 3 Pro 预览版”，
they would have just basically said, well, here's another new Gemini 3 Pro preview. Like they did
就像之前多次发布 2.5 预览版，直到最终推出正式版（GA）那样。
with say the 2.5 previews where they were multiple previews before we got to GA. It does seem
但现在看来，他们不再只是简单地推出一个带新日期的预览版，
here now that rather than just have another rollout of a new dated preview with a newer date kind of
而是决定将其命名为 Gemini 3.1 Pro。
thing, they've actually decided to call this Gemini 3.1 Pro. And those benchmarks, I think,
而这些基准测试成绩，我认为确实证明了这一命名的合理性。
really do justify that. So let's jump into having a play with this and see how it performs.
那我们现在就来实际体验一下，看看它的表现如何。
And I want to show you how you can actually take advantage of the different thinking levels
我想向大家展示如何利用这个模型的不同思维层级——
that this model has so that it can go from, you know, very quick thinking right up to things where
让它既能快速响应，也能在需要时花五分钟甚至更长时间给出完整答案。
you're looking at five minutes plus before you've got a full answer back. Okay, so to get started,
好，开始之前，请先切换到最新模型。
you come over here and you'll basically just select the latest model. So if you don't see it,
如果没看到，点击“全部”，它正在陆续推送中，你应该很快就能见到。
just click all, they're suddenly rolling it out. You should be able to see it pretty quickly in here.
我先用一道国际数学奥林匹克竞赛题来测试。
So I'm going to start off with one of the questions from the international math
去年我用深度思考模型运行这道题时，
Olympiad problem. Now this question, when I ran it last year with the deep think model, it was
它虽然给出了正确答案，但花了很长时间——我记得大概是……
able to give us the correct answer, but it took a long time, right? I think it was from memory
距离我们首次获得 token 已经过去了 17 分多钟。你可以看到，我们现在的设置是：
17 plus minutes before we were getting time to first token here. So you can see here we've got
我把思考级别设置为“高”。你可以看到，它确实需要花一些时间才能得出答案。
this setup. I've got thinking level set to high. And we can see that it's definitely taking, you
这主要是因为我们将思考级别设为了“高”。在 Gemini 3 Pro 的早期版本中，
know, time to get to, you know, to the answer. And this is partly because we've got the thinking level,
你只能选择“低”或“高”两种模式。
you know, set to high with the previous version of Gemini 3 pro, you could only have low or high.
但现在你可以选择“低”、“中”或“高”三种设置。你会注意到，在处理过程中，
Now you can have low medium or high as the setting in there. So you'll notice as it's going through
我们光是思考就已经花了两分钟左右。但我们期望的答案基本上是 0、1 和 3。
this, we're already sort of two minutes in of thinking. But the answer we're looking for here
让我们看看它最终能否得出正确答案。好的，我暂停了一下，
is basically 0, 1 and 3. So let's see if it's we're going to get the answer. Okay, so I paused it
当时它还在处理中。最终它确实得出了正确答案，但花了
while it was actually going through. It did finally come to the right answer. It took, you know,
超过八分钟才完成。这大约是 Deep Think 之前耗时的一半。
over eight minutes to get to this answer. That's roughly half of what deep think used to take.
但这正体现了这个模型一个非常有趣的特点。
But this shows one of the things that is really kind of interesting with this model.
也就是说，当你把思考级别设为“高”时，它的行为几乎就像是一个迷你版的 Gemini
And that's that if you have thinking set to high, this acts almost like a mini version of Gemini
Deep Think。这也是他们强调的一点：这个模型现在
Deep Think. And this is one of the things that they're kind of emphasized that this model now
已经从 Gemini Deep Think 的早期版本和最新版本中汲取了经验。
has taken sort of lessons from Gemini Deep Think, both the earlier versions and the more recent
但与此同时，如果我将它设为“低”，那么它的思考速度应该会快得多。
versions. Now at the same time, if I set this to low, right, we should get something that the
好的，虽然这次思考速度快了很多，但它实际上
thinking is much quicker on this. Okay, and so while the thinking was much faster here, it actually
并没有得出正确答案。所以在处理不同任务时，你确实需要根据情况调整思考级别。
didn't get the correct answer, you know, in this case. So you do want to make use of the thinking
另一个人们经常尝试的任务是创建 SVG 图像。这次我只是让它生成一张“骑着自行车的猫”的 SVG。
level when you're doing different tasks for this. So another task that people have been doing a lot
如果我们渲染出来，你会发现，嗯，这也许不是世界上最可爱的猫，
is creating SVGs. And this one is I've just asked it to make me the SVG of a cat writing a bicycle.
但效果还算不错。看起来猫还戴着围巾。
So if we render this out, you can see that, okay, yeah, it's perhaps not the best cat in the world,
自行车也画得相当准确，甚至还有链条。
but it comes out, you know, quite good. It looks like the cat's wearing a scarf. We've got
猫腿还踩在踏板上，这点做得挺到位的。
our bicycle, which looks pretty accurate. We've even got a chain. We've got the legs of the cat
如果你想亲自体验这个模型，可以直接进入 AI Studio 免费试用，
actually on the pedals, which is kind of good in there. Okay, so if you want to play with the model
尝试你自己的提示词。记住，最重要的是你要多尝试不同的
yourself, you can just come into AI Studio and try out the model for free and try out your own prompts
思考级别。如果你设为“高”，它可能需要更长时间才能给出答案，
and sort of see, remember, the big thing here is you should be experimenting with the different
但你会得到一个类似“Gemini Deepink Mini”的效果。
thinking levels. If you've got it set to high, it can take a lot longer to give you an answer.
该模型正在逐步推送给 Gemini Pro 用户，目前 Google Cloud 上已经可以使用。
But you're definitely getting sort of like a Gemini Deepink Mini out of this model when you do that.
如果你想在那里试用，当然也可以。虽然这次更新只是一个小版本（0.1），
So the model is rolling out to the Gemini Pro plan. It's already out on Google Cloud. If you want
但它实际上是一次重大升级，让模型重新回到了与 Opus 4.6 和最新 GPT 模型
to try it out there, you can certainly use it there as well. And I'd say that while this is an
相竞争的行列。就像三个月前 3 Pro 推动了专有模型和开源模型
incremental sort of point one step, it is a big update that basically gets the model back into
的飞速发展一样，现在 Gemini 3.1 Pro 正式发布并显著提升了性能，
the same sort of competitive area as Opus 4.6 and the latest GPT models as well. So just as
不禁让人好奇其他模型是否会推出新版本来追赶。
three Pro spurred a whole new sort of takeoff in both the sort of proprietary models and also the
好了，欢迎在评论区告诉我你的想法。我们下期视频再见，拜拜！
open model weights over the past three months, you've got to wonder now that Gemini 3.1 Pro is out
and actually has seriously bumped its performance, I'll be going to see other models release new
versions to try and catch up. Anyway, let me know what you think in the comments and as always,
I'll talk to you in the next video. Bye for now.